Hello everyone and welcome to EnglishPod.
大家好，欢迎收听EnglishPod。
My name is Marco.
我是Marco。
My name is Catherine and today we are cleaning, right Marco?
我是Catherine，今天我们打扫卫生，对吧Marco？
That's right.
没错。
Today we are cleaning our house.
今天我们要打扫房子。
It's not one of our favorite activities but we have to do it and so we're going to take
这不是我们最喜欢的活动之一，但我们必须做，所以我们要看看
a look at a lot of great vocab related to household chores.
很多与家务相关的好词汇。
That's right.
没错。
So let's take a listen to today's dialogue.
那么我们来听听今天的对话。
Kevin, what is this mess?
Kevin，这乱七八糟的是什么？
It looks like a pigsty in here.
这里看起来像个猪圈。
Clean this up.
把这个收拾干净。
Okay, dad.
好的，爸爸。
I will do it in a minute.
我马上做。
Let me just finish this level of this game.
让我先打完这关游戏。
No, I said now.
不，我说现在。
Plus, you are grounded.
另外，你被禁足了。
You're not allowed to play video games.
你不准玩电子游戏。
I want you to make your bed, do the laundry and then come downstairs and sweep the floors.
我要你整理床铺、洗衣服，然后下楼扫地。
That's so unfair.
这太不公平了。
You have to pull your weight around here, young man.
你得在这里尽自己的一份力，年轻人。
My house, my rules.
我的房子，我说了算。
And I already mopped the floors, dusted the furniture and vacuumed the rugs.
我已经拖了地板、擦了家具、吸了地毯。
That's great but you still have work to do so get to it.
那很好，但你还有活要干，所以赶紧去做。
So today on Language Takeaway, let's take a look at all the verbs and all the ways that
所以在今天的“语言要点”环节，我们来看看所有与打扫房子相关的动词和方式。
we have to clean the house.
So starting with the first one, we have to make the bed, make your bed.
从第一个开始，我们要整理床铺，整理你的床。
Make your bed.
整理你的床。
Okay, so this might sound quite strange because the verb to make is something we say for a
好的，这听起来可能有点奇怪，因为动词“make”在很多不同的事情上都会用到，比如“make a deal”（达成协议）。
lot of different things like make a deal.
“Make a mistake”（犯错误）。
Make a mistake.
But here, we're making the bed.
但在这里，我们在“make the bed”（整理床铺）。
That means we're putting the pillows on top of the bed and we're going to make sure the
这意味着我们把枕头放在床上，并确保毯子平整。
blanket is even.
So when you get out of bed, if everything is very messy, when you make it, you put everything
所以当你起床时，如果一切都很乱，当你整理时，你把床上所有东西都摆整齐。
in order on your bed.
That's right.
没错。
And well, it's also confusing because our next verb is to do the laundry.
而且，这也很让人困惑，因为我们的下一个动词是“do the laundry”（洗衣服）。
All right.
好的。
So you make your bed but you do the laundry.
所以你整理床铺，但洗衣服。
The laundry here means you clean the dirty clothes.
这里的“laundry”意思是清洗脏衣服。
Right, right.
对，对。
So this is one of the very, I would say, confusing parts of English where it's kind of confusing
所以这是英语中非常令人困惑的部分之一，就是什么时候用动词“make”，什么时候用动词“do”有点混乱。
when to use the verb make, when to use the verb do.
So usually, you make a mistake as we say or you make a cake but you do your homework.
所以通常，我们说“make a mistake”（犯错误）或“make a cake”（做蛋糕），但“do your homework”（做作业）。
So in these cases, you just kind of have to memorize that you make the bed but you do
所以在这些情况下，你只需要记住你“make the bed”（整理床铺），但“do the laundry”（洗衣服）。
the laundry.
Exactly.
完全正确。
So this is very common actually to do the laundry.
所以“do the laundry”实际上很常见。
I have to go do the laundry today because it's an event.
我今天得去洗衣服，因为这是一件大事。
You know, you have to gather your clothes and put in the detergent and wash it and dry
你知道，你得收集衣服，放洗衣粉，洗衣服，然后烘干。
it.
So just remember, make the bed, do the laundry but then how do we clean those floors?
所以只要记住，整理床铺，洗衣服，但我们怎么清洁地板呢？
All right.
好的。
So the floor, we have to do two things.
所以地板，我们得做两件事。
We sweep the floors.
我们扫地。
So the verb there is to sweep.
所以动词是“to sweep”（扫）。
And how do you sweep?
你怎么扫？
You actually use a broom to sweep.
你实际上用扫帚来扫。
So the broom is like a straw.
扫帚就像稻草一样。
It's like a brush almost that you use on the floor and you collect all of the hair and
它几乎像一把刷子，你用它在地板上，收集所有头发和灰尘之类的东西，然后倒进垃圾桶。
the dust and these things and you put it into the garbage bin.
But after you sweep, then you need to use water to clean because obviously, sweeping
但扫完之后，你需要用水来清洁，因为显然，扫地只适用于干的东西。
is just for dry things.
Mopping is actually how you clean with water and soap.
拖地实际上是你用水和肥皂清洁的方式。
That's right.
没错。
So now the verb there is to mop the floors and usually, you use water, you use soap and
所以现在动词是“to mop the floors”（拖地板），通常，你用水、肥皂和拖把。
you use a mop.
So you use a mop to mop.
所以你用拖把来拖地。
Exactly.
完全正确。
The verb is to mop.
动词是“to mop”（拖）。
The noun, the object is a mop like you say.
名词，物体是“a mop”（拖把），就像你说的。
So I'm going to mop the floors, right?
所以我要拖地板，对吧？
So please don't come into the kitchen.
所以请不要进厨房。
Right.
对。
Okay.
好的。
And well, now we need to clean the furniture and usually, on the furniture, we have a lot
而且，现在我们需要清洁家具，通常，家具上有很多
of dust.
灰尘。
So we need to dust the furniture, to dust.
所以我们需要给家具掸灰，掸灰。
To dust.
掸灰。
Yeah, this is something we don't use for the floors really because we have this great verb
是的，这个动词我们通常不用在地板上，因为我们有一个很棒的动词
to sweep.
扫地。
But with furniture and things like that, we say to dust and this means we're going to
但对于家具之类的东西，我们说掸灰，意思是我们准备
collect the dust off of the piano or the sofa or the table.
把钢琴、沙发或桌子上的灰尘收集起来。
Right.
对。
Exactly.
没错。
And now, the floors we clean, the furniture we clean, but sometimes we have rugs or we
现在，地板我们清洁，家具我们也清洁，但有时家里有地毯或
have carpet in our house, usually in the bedrooms or we have a large rug in the living room
有地毯，通常在卧室里，或者客厅里有一块大地毯，
and we need to clean that as well, but we don't really mop it and we don't sweep it.
我们也需要清洁它，但我们不会用拖把拖，也不会用扫帚扫。
It's best to vacuum it.
最好用吸尘器吸。
All right.
好的。
So the verb is to vacuum and what is the noun, the thing we use?
所以动词是吸尘，那名词呢，我们用的那个东西？
A vacuum cleaner.
吸尘器。
A vacuum cleaner or just simply a vacuum.
吸尘器，或者简单说吸尘器。
Now this is something that uses air to suck up all of the dirt and garbage.
这是一种利用空气吸走所有灰尘和垃圾的东西。
So it goes and it sucks up all of that bad stuff and so we don't have to dust it.
所以它会把那些脏东西都吸走，这样我们就不用掸灰了。
And obviously, with carpet, we can't really use water.
显然，对于地毯，我们不能用水。
Exactly.
没错。
So carpet is a great tool for cleaning fabric like carpets and rugs.
所以吸尘器是清洁地毯和地垫这类织物的好工具。
Very good.
很好。
So that's all the ways that we can basically, the verbs that we use to clean around the
所以基本上，这就是我们用来打扫
house.
房子的动词。
Let's listen to the dialogue again and we'll be back in a bit.
让我们再听一遍对话，一会儿回来。
Kevin, what is this mess?
凯文，这乱七八糟的是什么？
It looks like a pigsty in here.
这里看起来像个猪圈。
Clean this up.
收拾干净。
Okay, dad.
好的，爸爸。
I will do it in a minute.
我马上做。
Let me just finish this level of this game.
让我先打完这关游戏。
No.
不行。
Now, plus you are grounded.
现在，而且你被禁足了。
You're not allowed to play video games.
你不许玩电子游戏。
I want you to make your bed, do the laundry and then come downstairs and sweep the floors.
我要你整理床铺，洗衣服，然后下楼扫地。
That's so unfair.
太不公平了。
You have to pull your weight around here, young man.
你得在这里尽自己的一份力，年轻人。
My house, my rules.
我的房子，我的规矩。
But I already mopped the floors, dusted the furniture and vacuumed the rugs.
但我已经拖了地板，掸了家具，还吸了地毯。
That's great, but you still have work to do, so get to it.
很好，但你还有活要干，所以赶紧去。
All right, so now let's take a look at some phrases, three of them on Fluency Builder.
好了，现在让我们看看一些短语，在流利度构建器上有三个。
All right, now the first word here is pigsty.
好的，第一个词是猪圈。
The dad says, Kevin, it looks like a pigsty in here.
爸爸说，凯文，这里看起来像个猪圈。
Clean this up.
收拾干净。
Right, so a pigsty.
对，猪圈。
It looks like a pigsty.
看起来像个猪圈。
Now, a pigsty is where pigs live, right?
猪圈是猪住的地方，对吧？
That's right.
没错。
So, is it really a pigsty?
所以，真的是猪圈吗？
It's not really a pigsty.
不是真的猪圈。
There are no pigs living there, but to say that a room is like a pigsty means that it's
没有猪住在那里，但说一个房间像猪圈意思是它
very, very, very dirty.
非常非常脏。
Right.
对。
It looks almost like the mud and the dirty place where pigs live.
看起来几乎像猪住的泥泞肮脏的地方。
Exactly.
没错。
So, he's saying, you're living in a dirty room.
所以，他在说，你住在一个脏房间里。
You need to clean this.
你需要打扫一下。
Right.
对。
So, a room or a house will look like a pigsty.
所以，一个房间或房子会看起来像个猪圈。
Now, the dad is actually making him do a lot of work because he says the kid is grounded.
现在，爸爸实际上让他做很多活，因为他说孩子被禁足了。
You're grounded.
你被禁足了。
You're not allowed to play video games.
你不许玩电子游戏。
Now, a parent will ground a child, it's a verb, when the child does something bad.
父母会禁足孩子，这是一个动词，当孩子做了坏事时。
Right.
对。
So, maybe the child gets very, very bad grades at school and the parent says, ugh, you're
所以，也许孩子在学校成绩非常差，父母说，呃，你
grounded for one week.
被禁足一周。
That means you can't go out, you can't play video games.
这意味着你不能出去，不能玩电子游戏。
There are different rules in every family, but to say you're grounded means you're being
每个家庭有不同的规矩，但说你被禁足意味着你因为某事
punished for something.
受到惩罚。
Right.
对。
So, the verb is to ground and you can also be grounded.
所以，动词是禁足，你也可以被禁足。
And if you're grounded, you can say, I'm sorry, I can't go out today, I'm grounded.
如果你被禁足了，你可以说，对不起，我今天不能出去，我被禁足了。
Exactly.
没错。
So, to be grounded is not a fun situation, but obviously the father is saying, listen,
所以，被禁足不是一件有趣的事，但显然父亲在说，听着，
you're grounded.
你被禁足了。
You have time to do all of this work.
你有时间做所有这些活。
Right.
对。
And well, this is something that my dad used to say to me, well, you have to pull your
嗯，这是我爸爸以前常对我说的话，你得在这里
weight around here.
尽自己的一份力。
So, you have to pull your weight around here.
所以，你得在这里尽自己的一份力。
What does that mean?
那是什么意思？
To pull your weight.
尽自己的一份力。
Well, you think about it, if you're not carrying yourself, someone else is carrying you, it
嗯，你想想看，如果你不自己承担，别人就得替你承担，这
means that they're doing more work than they should be.
意味着他们做了超出自己本分的工作。
Right.
对。
So, you're basically being asked to do your part, to be responsible for yourself so that
所以，基本上就是要求你做好自己的事，对自己负责，这样
other people like your mom and dad don't have to be responsible for you.
其他人，比如你爸妈，就不用替你负责了。
Right.
对。
So, you have to help out and collaborate.
所以，你得帮忙并合作。
Exactly.
没错。
So, say there's three people, mom, dad, and a son.
比如说有三个人：妈妈、爸爸和一个儿子。
If mom does all the cleaning, all the cooking, all the washing, then the other two, they're
如果妈妈包揽了所有打扫、做饭、洗衣的活儿，那另外两个人就
not pulling their weight.
没有尽到自己的本分。
So, she says, pull your weight, do some cleaning, do some washing.
所以，她会说，尽你的本分，做点清洁，洗点衣服。
Right.
对。
So, if your mom cooks and then you wash the dishes, then you are pulling your weight.
所以，如果你妈妈做饭，然后你洗碗，那你就是在尽自己的本分。
You're helping.
你在帮忙。
You're helping out.
Exactly.
没错。
All right.
好的。
A lot of great stuff.
很多精彩的内容。
Let's take a listen to the dialogue one last time.
让我们最后再听一遍对话。
Kevin, what is this mess?
凯文，这乱七八糟的是什么？
It looks like a pigsty in here.
这里看起来像个猪圈。
Clean this up.
收拾干净。
Okay, dad.
好的，爸爸。
I will do it in a minute.
我马上做。
Let me just finish this level of this game.
让我先打完这关游戏。
No, I said now.
不，我说现在。
Plus, you are grounded.
另外，你被禁足了。
You're not allowed to play video games.
你不准玩电子游戏。
I want you to make your bed, do the laundry, and then come downstairs and sweep the floors.
我要你整理床铺、洗衣服，然后下楼扫地。
That's so unfair.
太不公平了。
You have to pull your weight around here, young man.
你得在这里尽自己的本分，年轻人。
My house, my rules.
我的房子，我的规矩。
But I already mopped the floors, dusted the furniture, and vacuumed the rugs.
但我已经拖了地板、擦了家具、还吸了地毯。
That's great, but you still have work to do, so get to it.
很好，但你还有活要干，所以赶紧去做。
Okay, very good.
好的，非常好。
So, doing household chores, not a fun thing.
所以，做家务可不是什么有趣的事。
But also, being grounded.
而且，还有被禁足。
Why do we consider chores to be kind of like a punishment?
为什么我们觉得家务活有点像惩罚呢？
Well, there's punishment where you sit alone in your room and you think about your actions,
嗯，有一种惩罚是让你独自坐在房间里反思自己的行为，
and then there's punishment that's more proactive.
还有一种惩罚更主动一些。
Mom and dad say, okay, well, he's grounded.
爸妈会说，好吧，他被禁足了。
Let's have him work.
让他干活吧。
Let's make him do something.
让他做点事。
Let's make him do something so that we're benefiting from his punishment.
让他做点事，这样我们就能从他的惩罚中受益。
I think it's also good when children are grounded because it makes them realize that they need
我觉得孩子被禁足时这样做也挺好，因为这能让他们意识到自己需要
to help out around the house.
在家里帮忙。
This work, it doesn't get done magically.
这些活儿不会凭空完成。
There's actually someone doing it.
实际上有人在干。
Right.
对。
And it's not like, well, in many cases in many countries, people will have, like we
而且不像，嗯，在很多情况下，很多国家，人们会有，就像我们
saw in our previous lesson, a domestic maid, a cleaning lady, that will usually do everything
在上一课看到的，一个家庭佣人、清洁女工，通常包揽所有活儿，
so maybe the kid will become very comfortable and not really do anything.
所以孩子可能会变得很安逸，什么都不做。
Or very lazy.
或者很懒。
Very lazy.
很懒。
Even worse, yeah.
甚至更糟，是啊。
So, I definitely remember in my house we had chores because when it's not punishment,
所以，我清楚地记得我家有家务活，因为当它不是惩罚时，
when it's your parents' expectation normally, that's called a chore.
当它是你父母的正常期望时，那就叫家务。
And they say, okay, Catherine, your chores this week, you need to take the garbage outside,
他们会说，好的，凯瑟琳，你这周的家务，你需要把垃圾拿出去，
you need to wash the dishes, and you need to make your bed every day.
你需要洗碗，还需要每天整理床铺。
And then maybe my brother had to help cook and clean the floor, mop the floors and sweep.
然后也许我哥哥得帮忙做饭、擦地板、拖地和扫地。
So we have different chores.
所以我们有不同的家务。
Right.
对。
And I guess this is more common especially if both parents work and everyone is collaborating
我想这更常见，尤其是如果父母都工作，每个人都在家里合作
or pulling their weight in the house.
或尽自己的本分。
And if you don't have a cleaning lady, for example.
而且如果你没有清洁女工，比如说。
Exactly.
没错。
Very interesting topic.
非常有趣的话题。
Well, that's all the time we have for today.
好了，今天的时间就到这里。
If you guys have any questions, any comments, you can find us at EnglishPod.com.
如果你们有任何问题、任何评论，可以在EnglishPod.com找到我们。
We hope to see you there.
我们希望能在那里见到你。
We'll see you guys.
我们下次见。
Bye.
再见。